YU SU: I'm super
excited here today
to talk about a
topic that is really
close to my heart,
language agents.
I'm very excited about this
topic in the past two years
or so.
It's really fascinating.
And I've devoted most
of my time thinking
about this, so I have to share
some thoughts here today.
Whether you like
it or not, well,
since you are in this lecture,
so most likely, you like it,
but you probably have heard
about the term agents a lot.
Many people are super
enthusiastic about it.
Bill Gates said
that it will bring
about the biggest revolution
since, essentially, GUI.
Then Andrew Ng said that
the agents workflows
will drive massive AI progress.
And then Sam Altman
said that 2025 is
the year when agents will work.
However, there is
definitely also
a lot of voice from the
other side of the aisle.
Many people think that the
current agents are just
thin wrappers around LLM.
So there is nothing
fundamental here.
Well, others think
autoregressive LLMs can never
truly reason or plan.
And then Auto GPT was one of the
early prototypes of these agent
systems.
It was very popular, so it's
the fastest growing repository
in GitHub history in
terms of number of stores.
But it didn't take
long for people
to realize that it was,
at least at the time,
more of a prototype, and that
there was a lot of limitations
from a production system.
If we take one step back
and think about, hey,
what is agents?
It's really not a
new thing, right?
It's one of the very first
topic we cover in AL11 agents,
especially using these
classic schematic illustration
from Russell and Norvig.
And it has been part of
the core pursuits of AI
since the very beginning.
So why, all of a sudden, it
became so much more popular
again?
So let's try to define
this modern agents.
Many people hold this view that,
hey, you have a language model.
It has a text in,
text out interface.
So the things that you
can do is quite limited.
It's still a lot,
but it's limited
because it's not connected
to external environments.
And then once you connect that
to an external environment,
you can perceive information
from the environment,
and you can exert impact
on the environment.
Then it becomes an agent.
That seems reasonable,
but at the same time,
it also seems a bit
oversimplified and incomplete.
We often hear things
like a self-reflection
that an agent or LLM looks
at its own reasoning process
and then autonomously
decide to do something else.
Or you can do multi-agent
simulation or lot
of other things that
don't necessarily
involve external
environment, or at least,
that's not part of the
core defining trait.
Fundamentally, I think there
are two main competing views
in the community.
The dominant view, I call
it an LLM-first view.
So first, I have an LLM.
It's amazing.
It's very powerful.
It knows a lot of things.
So let's make that
into an agent.
Then if you take this view,
naturally the implications are,
you think of building a
scaffold on top of an LLM.
And it will be a
lot of prompting.
And it will be heavy
on engineering.
And I think that's also
where a lot of the sentiments
that the agents are just thin
wrappers around LLMs come from.
I tend to take a different view.
I take an agent-based view.
So as I said, AI agents have
been the core pursuit of AI
since the very beginning.
And then just now,
they got an upgrade.
Now, we integrate one or more
LLMs into these AI agents,
so they gain a new
capability, to use
the language for reasoning
and communication.
If you hold this view,
then the implications
are all the same challenges
faced by the previous AI agents
like--
how to perceive
the environments?
How to reason about the
environmental state?
How to build world models to
model the state transition
dynamics in the environment?
And how to use that
for better planning?
All of these challenges
still remain,
but we need to re-examine them
through the new lens of LLMs.
And also, we need to
tackle the new challenges
and opportunities.
Now, we can do
synthetic data at scale,
we can do self-reflection,
and we can also do O1 style
internalized search.
OK?
If we agree on that view,
an agent-first view,
then we can look at what's
really fundamentally different
now once we're
integrating these LLMs.
I think it's really the
capability of using language
as a vehicle for reasoning
and communication.
The power of using the
language for communication
is probably more clear.
All of us remember vividly
the viral success of ChatGPT.
It was the fastest app to
grow to 100 million users
in human history.
But we also know that in terms
of the fundamental capabilities,
ChatGPT was not
significantly better
than the previous
generation, but OpenAI
decided to tune it
to be more chatty
and release it to the public.
So I think that really shows
you the power of using language
for communication.
You get instruction following.
You get in-context learning.
And you can easily
customize the output format.
But perhaps, a bit more
unique this time around,
because using language
for communication,
we have been doing that in
decades in dialogue systems.
But this new capability of
using language for reasoning
is probably a bit more
unique this time around.
It used to be the
case that I have
to do a lot of justification
about why this is unique,
but now, with all these
new reasoning models,
I think this has
become much easier.
But still consider this example.
Most people would look at
this example and think,
GPT-4 was being stupid
and contradicting itself.
If we start, the answer is
no, but with a lot a bit
more thinking, then it realizes
that the answer is actually yes.
But the way I see this
example, it really
shows the power of using
language for reasoning.
So the model can
decide on the fly
to use the adaptive amount of
compute for different problems.
So you've got a second chance.
Unlike in traditional ML models,
where you pay a fixed amount of
compute for any decision.
So you only have one shot,
and you have to commit to it.
And especially in the
context of agents,
reasoning is not just for
the sake of reasoning.
It's not just for
math or coding.
Reasoning is for better acting.
So you can use
reasoning to infer
about the environmental states,
you can do self-reflection,
you can do dynamic
replanning, but all
for the same purpose for
better acting, better
planning in the environment.
Now, we're ready to reconcile
this new generation of language
agents with the previous agents.
All we need to do is to add
a new type of action called
reasoning, by generating
tokens, in contrast with actions
in external environments.
Then for that, we also need to
add an internal environment,
just like an inner monologue
where reasoning happens.
With that change, now we
can also reconcile things
like self-reflection.
Now, it becomes just a
meta reasoning action,
it's a reasoning over
the reasoning process,
just like the
metacognitive functions.
And the reasoning is
for better acting.
And at the same time,
due to the power
of these LLMs, the perception
and the external action
spaces are drastically
expanded as well.
OK.
Before we proceed,
let me just provide
a little bit of justification
of the use of reasoning
here, because this is
such an overloaded term.
If we don't properly define it,
then people will frown upon it.
So I'm sympathetic
of the position
of you calling all of these as
reasoning, because for people
who are familiar with the
due process, mental model
of human cognition, by
the famous late Daniel
Kahneman in thinking
fast and slow,
you should be familiar with
concepts like perception,
then intuitive inference,
and then symbolic reasoning.
The intuitive inference
is fast, effortless.
And then symbolic reasoning
is slow and effortful.
But our LLMs don't have all
of those different cognitive
substrates for these different
type of cognitive functions.
All it has is mostly
just one mechanism,
which is token generation.
We will talk about this
later, because we will
talk about implicit reasoning.
But most of the
reasoning happens
through token generalization,
through explicit language
production.
So if you look at this
example from GPT-4o,
when it looks at this
image, its generation
incorporates all of these
different mental processes, what
we would call perception,
what's in there,
and intuitive inference,
what you can immediately
infer from what you see, and
also some symbolic reasoning,
some more complex reasoning.
So I think, for this reason,
because LLMs really only
have this one mechanism and
that blends all this together,
so I think it's proper
to call this reasoning.
And then one may alternatively
call these thoughts
to avoid this overloaded
term, but then the risk
is with the further
anthropomorphize these machines.
So I prefer reasoning
over thoughts.
Another thing that I want to
get behind us before we proceed
is the name.
There are so many different
names for these agents
right now-- these AI agents,
autonomous agents, LLMs agents,
and so on and so forth.
But I truly think language
agents is probably
the most discrete characteristic
name for this kind of generation
of agents, because
the language is really
the most salient traits.
And what about
multimodal agents?
Well, there is perception
in other modalities,
and they are very
important, but the language
is still doing the heavy
lifting, like the reasoning
and communication part.
And what about LLMs agents?
That's probably the most
popular name out there.
I think what's
really needed here
or characteristic of
this generation of agents
is this capability of universal
language understanding
and production,
which turns out to be
extremely important for agents.
But this capability doesn't
have to come from an LLM.
Maybe in a few days, we will go
beyond the LLM, but this need,
this capability will remain.
So LLMs could be
a means to an end.
In that sense, it's
less as fundamental.
So language agents is still
a more appropriate name.
If we take one step back and
think about the evolution of AI,
I think we're really entering
a new evolutionary stage
of machine intelligence.
So human intelligence is
truly a marvel made by nature.
Somehow, our brain
can take raw inputs
from different sensory
organs and represent them
in a unified neural
representation
to reconstruct the
world around us
and also to support symbolic
reasoning and decision making.
So that's truly fantastic.
Then throughout
the history of AI,
we have made many attempts to
approach human intelligence
and manifest
machine intelligence
into these AI agents.
But earlier generations
of AI agents
were only able to capture
some limited facets
of human intelligence,
like symbolic reasoning,
like perception in
single modalities.
Only recently was this
multimodal LLMs ends
with language agents
built on top of them.
For the first time,
we have a model
that can encode
multisensor inputs
into a unified neural
representation that
is also conducive to symbolic
reasoning and communication.
So this drastically improves the
expressiveness, the reasoning
ability, and the
adaptivity of AI agents.
And that's, I think, what makes
this generation of AI agents
so exciting.
We can do a more
detailed comparison
of these different
generations of agents,
but in the interest of
time, I will just quickly
go through this and just
focus on language agents.
The expressiveness
is pretty high.
For example, you can compare
with the logical agents, where
the expressiveness is bounded
by the logical language we use.
Here, the agent or the
model can essentially
encode almost
everything, especially
the verbalizable
parts of the world.
But for the
nonverbalizable parts,
like how to recognize
a face, we still
have multimodal encoders
to capture those.
And then for reasoning, now,
we do language-based reasoning
instead of logical inferences.
So it's fuzzy,
and it's flexible,
and it's semi-explicit.
So it's not entirely implicit.
You still have this
chain of thoughts
that you can see
what's going on.
And the fuzziness, I want
to emphasize that it's not
necessarily a bad thing,
because the world around us,
it has a lot of fuzziness in it.
If we resort to something
strictly very sound and very
rigid, then it comes as
a cost of sacrificing
the expressiveness a lot.
And then the adaptivity, which
is a hallmark of intelligence,
is also very high
in language agents,
because these are strong
prior captured by an LLM,
and the language used in
general is very flexible.
So before we proceed,
let me share with you
my own conceptual framework
for language agents.
This is what I have been using
to guide my own research agenda
in the past two years or so.
The most important things are
what I call core competencies.
And I try to arrange them
in a loose hierarchy.
So each box here,
you can roughly
find the corresponding cognitive
function in the human brain.
And then the bottom ones are
the more fundamental ones,
like perception,
memory, and embodiment.
And the upper ones built
on top of the bottom ones,
like planning built on top
of reasoning and word models,
and reasoning built on top
of perception and memory,
and so on, so forth.
We also have many
cross-cutting issues,
like safety, evaluation,
synthetic data
is both a challenge and an
opportunity, and efficiency,
and many new applications.
So with this
framework, now, you can
look at any new
paper about agents
and try to map its main
claims and main contributions
into this framework.
So that's the introduction.
And for the rest of
the talk, we will
try to cover three main
aspects of language agents.
How we model long-term
memory, for which,
I will use our recent
work, HippoRAG.
Then how do these language
models fully reason?
And I will use our work
on Grokked Transformer.
And then finally, I will talk
about planning, especially
word-based planning
using a word model.
OK.
So let's start with memory.
We'll talk about HippoRAG.
The main content will
be from HippoRAG,
but we'll talk about a lot
of other things as well.
It's a neurobiologically
inspired long-term memory
mechanism for large
language models.
It's led by my student,
Bernal, and in collaboration
with Michi from Stanford.
So if we look at how
humans or really,
most other animals that have a
nervous system, how they learn,
it's really fascinating that
we are all this 24/7, nonstop,
lifelong learners.
And all we learn is
stored in our memory.
So Eric Kandel, the
Nobel Prize winner
who got the prize
for his contribution
in the study of
memory, especially
the neurobiological
foundation of memory,
once said that
memory is everything.
Without it, we are
nothing, which, I think,
is very profound, because
really, anything we learn
has to be encoded in our memory
and through a process called
synaptic plasticity.
So basically, we can change
our synapses to memorize things
and to capture all the
things we're experiencing
and we're learning.
And there are different ways
of changing the synapses.
For example, you can change
the strength of the synapses
by either adding more
receptors here or releasing
more neurotransmitters.
Or you can do structural
changes to the synapses,
by growing new synapses for
the same neuron, for example.
So this is used, more often,
in forming long-term memory.
So we're really 24/7 learners.
Even when we are
sleeping, we are replaying
what happens during the day.
That's how this long-term
memory gets consolidated.
Ideally, we want the same kind
of learning capacity in machines
or especially, in agents as
well, because these agents, they
are supposed to
explore the world,
do things, and then
accumulate a lot of learning
from that, and
self-improve, in some sense.
However, that's very hard
for the current technologies.
For these neural networks, in
general, and this gigantic LLMs,
in particular, they
have the notorious issue
of catastrophic forgetting.
Because of these highly
distributional representation
in these models, when you
are learning new things,
it often has unintended
side effects,
like some other
things unexpectedly
got changed during that
new learning process.
And to illustrate this,
in the LLM context,
we can consider what
people have been
doing, trying to edit an
LLM to inject or alter
a specific effect.
So that's called
knowledge model editing.
And a hot topic in
LLMs model editing
is the so-called ripple effect.
So if you want to
change just this one
fact in a counterfactual
change, you want to say,
hey, Leonardo is a citizen of
Syria instead of United States.
And you have some
expected ripple effect,
because now, the
citizenship has changed,
so he should speak Arabic
instead of English.
But if you actually look at what
has changed after these edits,
you will see that a lot of other
unexpected things have changed,
or the things that should have
changed but didn't change.
So if you look at the negation
of these original statements,
you will see that it will still
predict Syria, which is wrong.
You want it to be United
States because of the negation.
And then the language
here also becomes Syria,
but you want it to be Arabic,
and so on and so forth.
So all of these just tell you
that because of this highly
distributional representation
of these artificial neural
networks, that makes
continual learning very hard.
The human brain
and animals somehow
figure out a way to do
that, but we don't quite
understand how that happens yet.
So we cannot replicate
that in machines.
But this kind of
continual learning
is highly desired for
agents and for LLMs.
So what can we do?
The good news is
that for LLMs, it's
possible to use an
alternative form of memory
called nonparametric memory.
So instead of directly
changing the parameters
of a model with the
new experiences,
we can just hold
the new experience
external to the model,
so it's nonparametric,
and then just retrieve them
using some mechanism as we go.
Of course, this is called a RAG,
Retrieval Augmented Generation.
But for that to work there is a
prerequisite condition, that is,
when you retrieve some external
information, and you say,
hey, this is your memory,
so you should take it
or your decision making
should be based on it.
Then it's based on the condition
that these LLMs actually
will be receptive to such
external information.
So we did this study
called adaptive comedian
or stubborn thoughts,
where we specifically
study this behavior.
When you have this
external evidence from RAG,
and then when that
directly conflict
within the LLM's parametric
memory, what would happen?
Will they resist that or will
they be receptive to that?
Perhaps, not too
surprisingly at this point,
but was very
surprising at the time
is that these LLMs
turned out to be highly
receptive to external
evidence, even
when that conflict with
their parametric memory.
So for the three
examples here, you
have a question and the
ground truth answer.
In this case, the parametric
memory of the LLM is correct.
But if you give it a coherent
counter memory like this,
then the LLM will happily accept
this and change its answer.
And in this case, the
parametric memory was wrong,
and you can correct that by
giving it the correct quantum
memory.
So that paves the way
for nonparametric memory
for LLMs because of
their being highly
receptive to this
external evidence.
Of course, this has other
implications like safety.
Maybe it means that these
LLMs could be highly callable,
but that's not the focus today.
OK.
Now, let's talk about how to
really make long-term memory
work for LLMs.
Most people know that RAG is
the de facto solution today.
You are given something that is,
for example, the LLMs doesn't
know or is beyond its
knowledge cutoff date.
Then it will retrieve
from the internet
and then use the
retrieved information
as a long-term memory
to answer the question.
But if you think
about how RAG works,
you embed this
evidence into vectors,
then you do vector-based
similarity to retrieve them,
that seems far simpler,
far less sophisticated
than the human memory system,
where we can recognize patterns
in massive data,
raw experiences.
We can create a lot of
associations across them.
And we can dynamically retrieve
them for the current context,
and so on and so forth.
So to illustrate some
of the limitations
of the current
embedding-based RAG system,
let's consider this example.
Let's say, you have a query--
which Stanford professor
works on the neuroscience
of Alzheimer's.
So you have two
salient concepts--
Stanford and Alzheimer's.
Then let's assume just
hypothetically, you
have a bunch of passages.
Each passage only contains
parts of the information.
So you don't happen to have
a passage that tells you,
this person is both a
Stanford professor and works
on Alzheimer's.
Instead, what you have is
these separate passages.
OK, this passage says this
person works at Stanford.
This passage says that this
person works on Alzheimer's.
And then you will see,
there is one person who
works at Stanford and
on Alzheimer's, but it's
in separate documents.
You don't happen to have one
document that tells you all.
So what would happen if you
just use embedding based on RAG?
Now, you embed each of these
passages into a vector.
You embed your
query into a vector.
You do compare these
similarities one by one.
Then you will find,
all of these passages
are equally likely
because each of them
captures precisely 50%
of the information.
And as a result, the
model has to manually go
through all of these
passages to figure out which
ones are the correct ones.
And you can imagine there,
could be thousands of professors
working at Stanford and
even more people working
on Alzheimer's.
So it's a one to many,
many to one relationship.
But our human memory
doesn't work that way.
Somehow, if we have come
across like this person works
on Alzheimer's, this person
also works at Stanford,
then we will build some sort of
association among them such that
when this query comes, we can
very easily and quickly find
that, hey, this person is
connected with both Stanford
and Alzheimer's.
So it's the answer.
We don't have to
go through, recall
all of this other information
to arrive at that conclusion.
So in that sense,
embedding based in RAG
works very differently
from human memory.
Now, to study how exactly how
the human memory works in these
regards, so we turn to this
well-established theory
of human long-term memory called
the hippocampal indexing theory.
It basically goes like this.
I'll summarize it in an
overly simplified way.
It says that your raw memory
is stored on your neocortex,
particularly, where the
memory was first generated.
So for an episodic memory,
the auditory part of it
will be stored in
the auditory cortex.
The visual part of it will be
stored in the visual cortex,
and so on and so forth.
That's why when you are
trying to recall something,
you were like
reliving the moments,
because it's just really
triggering the same neurons
as if you were perceiving them.
But importantly, you also
have a structured index
stored in the
hippocampus that creates
a much closer,
essentially, a shortcut
that associates all these
disparate memory units together.
And that's what we are
trying to mimic here.
This kind of separation
and structure index
gives you two important
faculties of human memory.
It allows you to do
pattern separation.
So you can differentiate
memories in a very fine-grained
way, certainly, beyond
just vectors, at least,
at the concept level.
If you think about your
episodic memory, this second
and the second before, they
are very similar to each other.
How can you differentiate
the differences?
That requires very fine-grained
separation of patterns.
But more importantly, which
is more relevant here,
is pattern completion.
We can recover complete memories
using just partial cues.
Like the previous example,
the partial cues are Stanford
and Alzheimer's.
And then you can quickly
recall this whole fact
that this person is
associated with both of them.
And that's due to
this structured index
in the hippocampus.
So that's what we're trying
to mimic in HippoRAG.
We're trying to build a similar
structured index for RAG systems
to enjoy some of
the same benefits
of the human long-term
memory system.
I won't get into
too much details,
so just at a high level, in the
hippocampal indexing theory,
there are three main parts--
there is the neocortex,
and the hippocampus,
and then there is the parahippo
regions that connects the two.
So the neocortex is more
about pattern separation.
So it will process
the raw experience,
extract patterns out
of these concepts,
and so on and so forth.
And then the hippocampus is
more like the structure index,
so it's the indexing
auto-association.
And then the
hippocampal regions is
more like the
working memory that
connects the two, then do
some more iterative thinking
around there.
So to mimic this process,
we have two spaces--
we have the offline indexing
phase and the online query
phase.
For the offline indexing, let's
say, you have these passages
as inputs.
We use an LLM to serve
as a neocortex that
will do open information
extraction to extract
these triplets--
the concepts, noun phrases,
and their relationships,
like the verb phrases.
So extract these
triplets, then we
do try to build a
knowledge graph.
Particularly, this is a
schema that's knowledge graph.
So we don't have an ontology,
or a predefined schema,
or anything like that.
Everything is extracted by an
LLM from the raw experiences.
So we built a knowledge
graph by consolidating
all these newly extracted
concepts and phrases
as nodes and edges.
That's the offline
indexing phase.
And this becomes our
artificial hippocampal index.
Then we use a dense
retrieval here as an encoder
to consolidate
things, to identify
which concepts are similar
to each other or synonymous
to each other.
Then in the online retrieval
phase, when a query comes in,
like the Stanford
assignment example,
then we'll identify the concept.
We use named entity recognition.
So now, we'll get the
Stanford and Alzheimer's.
We still use a dense
retrieval to find
the similar nodes in my index.
And then those nodes become the
seed nodes for the graph search
process.
So we will use these as seeds to
do a search process on the graph
to find the most related things.
And this particular graph search
algorithm we're using here
is Personalized PageRank.
OK.
So for people who
don't quite remember
what a Personalized PageRank
works, I'll do a quick recap.
So it's a random walk
process on the graph, where
you start with some seed nodes.
So those start
with probability 1.
Then you use a random walk
starting from the seed
nodes to disperse
the probability mass
to their neighboring nodes.
So the nodes that are
closer to these seed
nodes or especially, those
that are in intersection
of multiple seed
nodes will naturally
end up with a higher weights.
Then in this case,
Professor Thomas,
who is connected to both
Stanford and Alzheimer's
will naturally stand out and
getting the highest weights.
Then we can use these
weights over concept
to reweight the
original passages,
then to retrieve the most
highly weighted passage.
So that's how HippoRAG
works in a nutshell.
Of course, there are a lot of
details that we're not covering,
but this is the main gist.
And it turns out,
some simple strategy
like this, biologically
plausible strategy,
works also extremely
well in practice.
It's not enough.
It is, of course, a neat
idea, like, hey, this
is biologically inspired.
How good is that?
But I think it's
equally important for it
to actually work, to work very
well and better than existing
solutions in practice.
And that's what we
showed with HippoRAG.
So we'll compare HippoRAG with
the state-of-the-art dense
retrievers at the time and show
that three standard multi-hop QA
datasets, it performs much
better by a large margin.
And also, you can
compare HippoRAG
with this iterative
retrieval methods like IRCoT.
And it also works better
than this iterative method,
and also because HippoRAG,
the nature of it, really,
this structured index
and this graph search,
so it's highly complementary
to all these existing methods.
You can easily integrate it
with other methods like IRCoT.
And then you get a
big boost as well.
OK.
And to better understand where
does this power of HippoRAG
comes from, we can consider
a type of questions,
what we call
path-finding questions,
like the running example
we have been working with.
So if you think about,
in this information
space, like this huge graph
of everything connected
to everything,
what's the solution
path or structure for
this question looks like?
You will see, it's not just a
one to one to one kind of task,
you first start with a
one to many relation.
Like Stanford, there are many
professors working at Stanford.
Then among those is our
answer, Professor Thomas.
And then from the
people to researchers
to Alzheimer's, that's also
a many to one relationship.
So there are many people
working on Alzheimer's.
If you don't have prior
knowledge about the answer
you're looking for,
then naturally, you'd
have to search through all
these hundreds of thousands
of candidates for you to
find Professor Thomas.
And HippoRAG, by explicitly
extracting, and building
these associations
from the raw inputs,
that allows you to create
these shortcuts to quickly find
the true answer.
While if you use
ColBERT or IRCoT,
then they won't be able
to find it efficiently.
OK.
So that was HippoRAG.
That was published in NeurIPS,
which is just two months ago,
but in today's pace,
it feels like ages ago.
So I'm very excited to
share that HippoRAG v2 is
coming very soon.
And so a problem with HippoRAG,
all these recent structured
augmented RAG methods, like
GraphRAG, LightRAG, RAPTOR,
and so on and so forth.
If you compare favorably
to this simpler baselines
like these small
dense retrievals
like ColBERT v2 or Contriever.
But recently, there have been
many large embedding models,
like Grit, like NV-Embed.
And if you actually compare
these structured augmented RAG
methods with them, you will
see that they are much worse,
including HippoRAG.
They are working compare OK
on these multi-HOP QA tasks
because they will
mostly be designed
for these kind of tasks.
But if you just look
at other scenarios,
like just some very simple QA
or some discourse understanding,
and so on and so forth,
they don't work that well.
So as a result, it's very
hard for these methods
to become just a
drop in replacement
of embedding-based methods.
Then in HippoRAG v2, we did
a bunch of clever upgrades
to HippoRAG v1.
And the result is
that now, v2 is
comparable or better
than the best logic
embedding models
across the board.
So then it's much more
plausible to just use
HippoRAG v2 as a drop in
replacement for your RAG system.
We hope to release
this very soon.
So for the memory
part, the takeaways,
so memory is really
central to human learning.
And long-term memory through
parametric continual learning
for LLMs is very hard.
But fortunately,
non-parametric memory like RAG
could be a promising solution.
And the recent trend in RAG
is to add more structures
to embeddings, like
HippoRAG or GraphRAG,
to enhance the sense-making
capability of these models,
like the ability to
integrate larger, more
complex, and uncertain
contexts, and the associativity
of these memory,
like the capacity
to draw multi-HOP connections
between disparate pieces
of information.
OK?
So that's memory.
And I think we're
still quite far away
from developing a very
sophisticated memory system,
but we are getting there.
But there are still
many gaps like how
to handle like episodic memory,
the spatial temporal aspects
of things, which is
central to human memory.
We don't have a
good solution yet.
OK.
So memory is the most
fundamental aspects
in my opinion.
Then let's get to another
very fundamental aspect, which
can be built on top of
memory, which is reasoning.
And our discussion today
will be mainly based
on this paper,
Grokking of Implicit
Relations in Transformers.
It's led by the student
from our group, Boshi Wang.
And it's published
in NeurIPS last year.
All right.
So we will be talking
about implicit reasoning.
In implicit reasoning, we
don't do chain of thought.
So there is no verbalized
chain of thoughts explicitly.
We ask the LLM to directly
predict the answer.
In this example of
compositional reasoning,
let's say, the language model
has memorized or know these two
atomic facts that
Barack's wife is Michelle,
and Michelle was born in 1964.
Then the model will be given
these inputs, like Barack,
wife, born in, and is
asked to directly predict
the answer, 1964, in this
compositional reasoning fashion.
So if you do chain of
thoughts, of course,
you can try to recall, hey,
Barack's wife is Michelle.
Michelle was born in this.
So therefore, the
answer is this.
But we want to push the
model to implicitly just
using its parameters in
a single forward pass
to do this reasoning.
Why?
CoT, especially this long CoT
is all the rage right now,
like in R1 or o1.
And why does implicit
reasoning matter?
This is also, in
the beginning, why
the reasoning
mechanism of these LLMs
is mostly just token generation,
but implicit reasoning
is still part of the
reasoning repertoire.
So why does implicit
reasoning matter?
First of all, this
is the default mode
of training or pre-training.
Because during training
time, when the model
is asked to predict the next
token with cross-entropy loss,
there is no CoT, at
least, not for now.
So in training time, model
has to compress the data.
It has to do implicit reasoning
in order to reasonably predict
the next token.
So no matter what, I think
it's important to understand
the implicit reasoning
capability of language models.
Also, implicit
reasoning fundamentally
determines how well
these models acquire
structured representations
of the facts
and the rules from
their training data.
And finally, there is
a lot of speculation
about how these o1 or R1
style long CoT emerge from RL.
I think, one plausible
hypothesis, as it is in my mind,
is like this.
You start with a
capable base model.
If the base model is not capable
enough, then RL won't do much.
So you start with the capable
base model, like DeepSeek v3.
And it probably
has already learned
all of these basic
constructs or strategies
for reasoning, so
like self-reflection,
like analogical reasoning,
and so on and so forth,
maybe in implicit
reasoning fashion,
just some kind of reasoning
circuits in the parameters.
Then reinforcement learning
was these verifiable rewards,
is just to incentivize
the model to learn
to use the right
combination of strategies.
But it's not learning new
reasoning strategies through RL.
And then it also encourages
the model to keep trying
and don't be lazy.
So if this hypothesis
is true, then
understand how these
different reasoning strategies
work within the model
becomes even more important.
So back to implicit
reasoning, before our work,
there were a bunch of
work, a great work that
shows that LLMs truly struggle
with implicit reasoning.
Some people show
that it struggles
with compositional
reasoning like this.
There is a famous
compositionality gap.
And then some other
people show that LLMs,
even GPT-4 at the time,
struggled with simple things
like comparative
reasoning or comparison.
Like, Trump is 78,
Biden is 82, then
Trump is younger or
older than Biden.
So that was the
previous conclusions,
but we had different opinions.
It seems to us,
this all contribute
to this autoregressive LLMs
and never truly reason or plan,
narrative.
But we had some
different beliefs,
we have more faith, more
confidence in language models
and transformers.
So we want to more
carefully study this problem
and to see whether we can
get some new insights.
So we started with this
research questions-- first,
can transformers learn
to reason implicitly,
or are there
fundamental limitations
that prohibit robust
acquisition of this skill?
And then what factors?
Is that the scale of the
training data, the distribution
of the training data, or
the model architecture
that control the acquisition
of implicit reasoning?
OK?
So with these two questions,
let's discuss the setup.
The model and optimization
are pretty standard.
I don't want to
introduce questions here.
So it's just like
a standard decoder
only transformer in
GPT-2 architecture.
And we'll also show
that the results
are pretty robust to
different model scales.
So you can have a deeper
model, but the conclusions
are the same.
And then the optimization
is also pretty standard.
Then for the data we'll be
using will be synthetic data,
because we want to
carefully control
all the factors in
this investigation
so that we can separate out
the problem we want to study.
Let's just consider composition.
We study both composition
and comparison,
but let's focus on
composition for now.
The data will look like just
a random knowledge graph.
It has epsilon entities
and R relations.
We set R to 200.
So then it's a bunch
of nodes and then
these different
relations like this.
Then these are the atomic facts.
Like, superstition
singer is Stevie.
And then we can use
these atomic facts
to get some inferred facts
or these two-hop compositions
following the composition rule.
If the head entity, r1, bridge
entity, and then bridge entity,
r2, tail entity, then we
have this composition effect,
like head entity,
r1, r2, tail entity.
So it's like Barack,
wife, born in, 1964.
So this composition, and you can
think, the data for comparison
is similar.
OK?
Then the important
setup here is that we
want to study inductive
learning of deduction rules.
A fancy phrase, but let me
just decompose this for you.
First of all, we
want the model, which
is the decoder-only transformer,
to learn inductively.
So just give a bunch
of training examples.
You want to learn these rules.
And particularly, these
are deduction rules.
So this is a typical
deduction rule.
You start from some premises and
then you can deduce new facts.
So this is inductive
learning of deduction rules.
Then there are two
generalization settings,
what we call the
in-distribution setting and then
the out-of-distribution
setting, or this setting
can also be called
systematic generalization.
So it goes like this.
For the atomic facts, like those
edges in the knowledge graph,
we split it into two sets--
the ID set and the OOD set.
Then we all go through the same
rule, the composition rule,
you get the corresponding
inferred facts.
Then for this set of inferred
facts from the ID atomic facts,
we split it into two sets--
the training set
and the ID test set.
So for these inferred facts,
put in the ID test sets.
Even though we have not
seen these exact inferred
facts in our training data, so
it's an unseen inferred effect,
but we have seen all
of its constitutes
like those atomic facts, being
composed with other atomic facts
in these ID training sets.
I know it's a bit of a
mouthful, but just bear with me.
So for any of these inferred
facts in the ID test
set, like, Barack,
wife, born in,
1964, maybe you have not
seen that exact inferred fact
in your training
data, but you have
seen, like for
example, the relation,
like Barack, wife, Michelle.
You have seen these
atomic facts being
composed with other relations.
Also, similarly, you have
seen the other atomic facts,
like Michelle born in
1964, being composed
with other atomic facts.
You just haven't happened to
see that exact inferred fact,
like Barack, wife, born
in 1964, so that you still
need some generalization
to capture them.
For the ODD test
set, then you still
have seen all of
the atomic facts
because otherwise,
the model doesn't
know that these facts exist.
But you have never seen any
of those atomic facts being
composed in a
compositional fashion,
being composed with
other relations.
So in that sense, it's a
stronger generalization setting,
so that's why it's called the
systematic generalization.
If the model can do
this, then essentially,
it means that the model has
truly learned this deduction
rule, so that you can just apply
it to any arbitrary new facts.
So that's really the
goal for this learning
of deduction rules.
Now, with all this vanity
set up in minds, let's look
at some fun parts, look at
some interesting takeaways
from our investigation.
The first surprising
conclusion we found
is that transformers can
learn to reason implicitly,
but only through a
process called grokking.
What is grokking?
So let's look at
this figure for now.
This curve is the
training accuracy.
You can see, it quickly
goes to 100%, that means,
the training has
overfit at these points.
But if you look at
the ID test curve,
when the model
first overfits here,
the test accuracy
was still very low.
And if you keep training the
model way beyond the saturation
or overfitting, the overfitting
happens around like 10,000
steps.
And if you train it like 20
times more optimization steps,
to these points, this is
log scale, for example,
keep in mind.
Then all of a sudden, at least,
the ID generalization happens.
So the model gets to
100% test accuracy
on composition in the ID split.
Similarly, for comparison,
the overfitting
happens very early
on, but it takes
about 20 more times of
training optimization steps
for generalization to happen.
And interestingly,
for comparison,
all the test accuracy
also get to 100%.
So that's a problem
we'll look into later.
So that's quite interesting.
This transformers,
they can learn
to reason implicitly but
only through rocking.
And it's one of the first
studies that establishes
this connection between
rocking and implicit reasoning,
I believe.
And we will investigate why
that happens in a second.
Another immediate takeaway
here is that, as we just said,
this level of systematicity
of generalization
varies by the reasoning type.
For compositional
reasoning, it never
managed to learn
to generalize OOD.
Well, for comparative reasoning,
OOD generalization did happen.
So we want to
understand why there
is such a difference as well.
Then another interesting
takeaway here is that,
so before this study, there
were already some studies
that looked at grokking.
And then try to understand,
why grokking happens?
And under what conditions
would grokking happen?
Then one common belief
in the literature
was that there is a
critical data size.
Once your total amount of data
surpasses a certain threshold,
then grokking happens,
otherwise, it won't happen.
But in our study, we tried
to study this hypothesis
very carefully.
Then we find that actually, it's
not the data size but the data
distribution that matters.
So in these experiments,
on the right, we keep the--
so there is two variables.
There is the total
data size, which
is controlled by the
number of entities,
and it's proportional
to the total number
of training examples.
And then there is phi, which
is the ratio of the inferred
versus atomic facts.
So if this number
is larger, that
means that you have
more input effects
than you have atomic effects.
So on the right, we
keep the ratio fixed
and increase the number of
entities or the total data size.
Then you will see, the
speed of generalization
is roughly the same when you
increase the total data size.
It's, more or less, the same.
However, when you keep
the data size fixed,
so it's the same
number of entities,
you just change the ratio
phi, from 3.6 to 18.
Then you see, the
speed of generalization
strongly positively
correlates with this ratio.
If you have a higher ratio,
then the generalization
will happen faster.
And at some point,
it will be as fast
as the overfitting
of the training data.
So this really shows that
it's the critical data
distribution that matters, not
the sheer size of your training
data.
Well, with all those
interesting takeaways,
our job is not done here
yet, because there are still
some very important questions
we have not answered.
So why does grokking happen?
What exactly happens during
this long grokking process?
What's going on
within the model?
And why does the level
of systematicity,
in generalization, vary
by the reasoning type?
So all of these
questions require
a deeper look inside the model.
That's the mechanistic
interpretation part
of this study.
So we will use some
popular and nowadays,
very standard mechanistic
interpretation tools.
One is logit lens.
So here, we apply
the internal states
at some position
within the transformer
and multiply it with the
output embedding matrix
so that we can get a
distribution over the output
vocabulary.
So we get a peek into what
this internal representation
is about.
Then we will also use the
so-called causal tracing.
In a nutshell, this
technique allows
you to quantitatively
measure the amount
of the impact of a certain
internal state to the output.
So it ranges from 0 to 1.
If it's closer to 1, that
means that this position,
this internal state has a larger
impact on the final decision.
I won't get into
the very details
because that will
take too much time.
So with this mechanistic
interpretation techniques,
now, we can try to
find or discover,
rather, that the corresponding
generalized circuits formed
for a different reason types.
And this is what we
found, very beautiful.
We find that for
composition, after grokking,
the transformer will learn a
generalizing circuit like this.
It's a kind of
dangerous circuit.
So this is the input
to the transformer.
You have the head
entity, r1, and r2.
And then this is
the layer 0, this
is layer 8, the final layer.
Then the first few
layers of the transformer
will essentially do two things--
for these parts, it will process
the first hop, essentially,
to look at h and r1, and then
find the bridge entity, b.
Here, we're using
logical density here.
So it has memorized these atomic
facts in the first few layers
to the extent that it can
reliably predict b at layer 5.
Then another thing that
needs to be done here
is that it needs to defer
the processing of r2.
So you cannot forget about r2
because r2 needs to be used
later.
Even though it.
doesn't need to use r2
in the early layers,
it needs to use r2 when it has
found b, the bridge entity.
OK?
So once the bridge
entity is identified,
then in the internal states,
then it can be combined with r2.
And then it has memorized the
atomic facts that b, r2 is t.
So then you can combine the
bridge entity and the data
processing of r2 to predict t.
So that's the generalizing
circuit for composition,
it has two clear stages.
And that will also determine
its generalization behavior
that we'll analyze later.
But on the other hand, the
comparison relationship
or reasoning has a
different circuit, what
we call a parallel circuit.
Remember, for comparison, it's
like, you have two entities,
e1 and e2.
You have some attributes of this
entity, like, this is Trump,
this is Biden.
And then Trump is v1 is 78.
Biden is 82.
Then the prediction is like,
Trump is younger or older
or equals than Biden, right?
Then the circuit here is
more of a parallel circuit.
So the first few layers
of the transformer
will learn to, in parallel,
retrieve the attribute values,
like 78 and 82.
Then the upper layers will
use these retrieved values
to do the comparison and then
to predict the final answer,
whether it's smaller
than, equal, or larger.
OK?
So given the reason through
mechanical interpretation,
we can find the generalizing
circuit's configuration
of different reasoning types,
and they are, indeed, different.
And this different
configuration will
determine their level of
systematicity of generalization.
But before that, let
me share a simple way
to fix or to improve this
systematic generalization,
especially for composition.
So as we showed earlier,
for composition,
OOD generalization
never happened.
Why?
If you look at this
circuit and think about it,
that becomes obvious.
So for the ODD
generalization to happen,
the model needs to
do a few things.
It needs to first
memorize a copy
of the first half atomic
facts, like h, r1,
b in the lower layers
of the transformer,
so that you can find the
bridge entity at the layer 5.
Then it also needs
to store a copy
of the second half atomic
facts, but in the upper layers,
because the second half has a
delayed processing, so it needs
to somehow store
the atomic facts,
b, r2, t here, not in the lower
layer, but in the upper layer.
However, for the
OOD generalization,
remember, our
definition of ODD is
that none of these
atomic facts has
been seen during training to
be composed with other facts.
In that situation, the
model has no incentive
to store this second half of the
atomic fact in the upper layers.
It only seen this atomic
fact individually,
so it can easily memorize
them in the lower layers,
but it doesn't
have the incentive
to store another copy
in the upper layers,
because that requires
extra effort.
That's why ODD generalization
of composition never happens.
Well, for comparison, you don't
have this stage of processing.
So you only need to store one
copy of the atomic effect.
And you can retrieve the
value in the lower layers
here for the comparison.
So you don't have
that issue, and that's
why ODD generalization of
comparison does happen.
OK?
And to further validate
this hypothesis,
we did an intervention here.
So if that is indeed
the case, that
is because the model
doesn't have an incentive
to store this atomic
fact in the upper layers,
then we just need to do some
cross-layer parameter sharing.
So you tie the weights
of the lower layers
with the weights
of the upper layer,
so it's a parameter sharing.
And then if the lower layer
has memorized the atomic facts,
then the upper layer will
get a copy of it as well.
So we did that intervention.
And it turns out, boom,
all the generalization
starts to happen
for composition.
So this further
validates the hypothesis.
It's a bit dense, but I
think that this is probably
one of the most interesting
slides or analysis of this work.
So remember, we try to
understand what exactly
is going on during grokking.
We said that the
grokking process
is when these generalizing
circuits start to form,
but in what exact way?
That's still unclear.
So through causal
tracing, we can actually
identify what exactly is
going on during grokking.
Let's first focus
on this figure.
Let me first say this.
So we believe, grokking is the
phase transition from rooted
learning to generalization.
So grokking starts
when the model
has overfit the training data.
But at that point, the model
has only done rote learning,
so it just [INAUDIBLE] memorized
all the training data, including
the inferred facts, but not
actually in a generalizable way.
But because it has
memorized all of them,
so the training
loss will be zero,
but it doesn't mean
that it has captured
this generalizing circuit.
Then the grokking
process is essentially
the phase transition from
the initial rote learning
to the generalization.
And it's where this generalizing
circuit gets formed.
And now, let's analyze how
exactly it gets formed.
The first thing we will
look at is this figure.
We look at two things.
So S, 5, r1 is this position.
This is S stands for states.
So this is a state of layer
5 as the position of r1.
So it's this one, S5, r1.
Then we can use
logical dense to decode
what's captured in that state
representation, in that state.
You can see, the
grokking process,
and similarly, we can do that
for S, r5, r2, so this position.
So once grokking starts,
the model already has,
and this is MRR, so it's
the Mean Reciprocal Rank.
But basically, it
just tells you,
the ranking of the bridge
NCP in the logic dense.
If it's one, it means that
the state here will always
predict the bridge entity
b, so that means that it
has encoded this information.
So when the grokking
starts, b is already there,
the MRR equals 1.
So that means, this
state here always
predicts the bridge entity
b, which is what we want.
We want the first half to
get us the bridge entity.
That is great.
But remember, we
also need the model
to do a delayed processing
of r2, so that at this point,
it can combine b and r2 to
predict the tail entity t.
But if you look at MRR of
r2 at this position, when
grokking starts, it
does not have r2 there.
So it has to be here, but
it doesn't have r2 here.
Despite that, so this
is on the training set.
So the model has a
training loss of 0.
So the model can perfectly
predict the tail entity,
despite not using r2
here, to combine with b.
That means the model is
just doing rote learning.
So it just memorize that,
hey, whenever I see h, r1, r2,
then I will predict t,
but it's not actually
doing this staged thing like
getting the bridge entity
and then combined with r2
to use another atomic fact
and do the reasoning.
But through the grokking
process, you can see,
the r2 gradually increases.
So at the end of a grokking,
it always predicts r2.
Then you have t here,
you have r2 here,
then you can actually
recall the atomic facts here
to predict the t entity.
So this is further corroborated
by the causal tracing results
here.
So remember, through
causal tracing,
we can quantify the causal
strength of each state
to the final prediction.
And this is the causal
strength of each state
at the beginning of grokking.
And this is after grokking.
Now, we can calculate the
difference between the two
and find their diff.
You can see, the diff mainly
happens here at S5, r1.
So that means, in the
beginning of grokking,
even though the model has
the bridge entity be here,
it does not use it.
It just did rote learning, so it
directly predicts the t entity.
But the grokking
process is the process
of the model learning to use
this bridge entity properly,
so giving it a stronger
causal strength
to the final prediction.
And this, combined with
the fact that we just shown
that through logic
dense, that's r2,
the grokking process is where
these r2 start to emerge.
These, combined,
validates the hypothesis
that this grokking
process is really
the process of forming these
generalized circuits, this stage
circuits that we just
shown for composition.
And we can actually explain,
even though we didn't
do any proof of any
sort, but you can roughly
understand why this kind
of grasping behavior
happens through the
circuit efficiency
and the regularization.
The generalizing circuits
is much more efficient
than the memorizing circuit,
the circuit for rote learning.
And because you also
have regularization,
the l2 regularization
term, for example.
Then if you just keep training,
even after overfitting,
the regularization
term will decrease.
And then it will gradually
favor the circuit
with higher efficiency, which
is the generalizing circuit.
So that's why you find it still
beneficial to train way over
beyond overfitting,
because that's
when the regularization
starts to kick in
and gets you the more
efficient circuit.
But at least let me give you
the definition of planning,
because that, in itself,
is a very confusing thing
for various reasons.
So in the context
of language agents,
we will work with this
simplified definition
of planning.
Given a goal, g, decides
on the sequence of actions,
a0 to an, that will
lead to a state that
will pass the goal test, g.
So of course, this is
all very simplified
because we don't talk about the
state space, the observation
space.
And then the actions, they're
not just atomic actions,
they have
preconditions that have
to be met before they can be
taken, and so on and so forth.
But for this
purpose, I think it's
enough to have this definition.
Then with this definition, we
can analyze these general trends
in planning settings
for language agents,
compared with the classic
planning setting, which
has been studied for decades.
Generally, I think,
the expressiveness
in goal specification is
drastically increasing.
So now, we can express our goal
in natural language as opposed
to some formal language,
which is usually much more
limited in expressiveness.
And also, we have a
substantially expanded
or open-ended action space.
So instead of some very
constrained action space,
like, hey, you have a
robot, you can move forward,
you can turn left, and
so on and so forth.
Now, you can have an even
open-ended action space.
And we will see some
examples soon later.
Then because of those,
it becomes increasingly
hard to automate the goal test.
Imagine, you have a
web agent that is just
doing things on the web.
Then a lot of the time, you just
simply cannot just write a goal
test beforehand.
What the goal
state will be like?
But that's fine,
because fuzziness
is really inherent
part of this world.
I'll skip this one.
So I just give some examples for
web agents, from our mighty web.
You'll see, in terms of
the goal specification,
the user can ask for anything
on an arbitrary website.
So it's very broad
in natural language.
And then in terms
of the action space,
you have some broad
actions, like you can type,
you can click, you can drag,
you can hover on some elements.
But the actual actions, like
what elements you click on,
these actual actions are
dynamically populated
on each web page.
So if you go to a
different web page,
your action space
will be different.
And it's a very
big action space.
You have to discover on the fly.
And of course, the goal
test is also very hard.
And then there's another
example of trial planning
that has some similar
characteristics,
but we'll skip here.
So I think these are some of
the general trends for language
agent planning.
And I think, these
are good trends.
Yeah, it makes things
more challenging,
but for the better,
because now, we
can support much more realistic
and useful application scenarios
with these language agents.
So let's see what you all want
to talk about this, maybe,
very quickly.
But for people who are
interested in web agents
or computer user
agents, I encourage
you to look at these
series of work.
Like Mind2Web, the first
LLM-based web agents, and then
SeeAct, where we first
introduced visual perception
into web agents,
and then UGround,
where, for the first time, we
make a human-like embodiment
for computer use agents.
So you only perceive the
environment visually.
There is no HTML or
anything like that.
And then you directly do
pixel-level operations
on the screen.
And this minimalist
design actually
works the best across the board.
And then we will talk
about WebDreamer,
which is model-based
planning for web agents.
OK?
So let's consider the
different planning paradigms
for language agents.
The most common one is
reactive planning or react.
Imagine, each node
here is a web page.
Then at each stage, you have
several candidate actions
you can take that will
result in a different state.
For reactive planning,
you just, at each stage,
observe the environment, reason
about it, then make a decision,
and commit to the
decision, and then
that gets you to another state,
then you just keep doing this.
So it's fast, it's
easy to implement,
but the downside is that it's
greedy and it's short-sighted.
So you often find yourself
stuck in some bad state.
And there's no way out.
Then naturally, when
we talk about planning,
we just think about
search or tree search.
So for tree search, compared
with reactive planning,
you can do backtracking.
You maintain a value assignment
for the states on your search
frontier.
Then you explore the
most promising branch.
At some point, if you find that
not promising, you can backtrack
and then you try to
explore another branch.
So that gives you more
systematic exploration.
But the downside
here is that it's
in real-world environments
like the internet.
There are a lot of
irreversible actions
that makes backtracking
impossible or at least,
very hard.
And then a lot of
this exploration
could also be unsafe or slow.
To just show you how pervasive
this state-changing and
irreversible actions are
in real-world environments,
let's consider just amazon.com.
On this single website,
you can have dozens, if not
hundreds of these
state-changing actions.
You can place an order.
You can make a return.
You can create an account that
you will agree to the terms
and use.
And then that has
legal implications.
You can change your
privacy settings,
and so on and so forth.
If there is no like this
universal magical Undo button
that you can just try a bunch
of things and then magically
undo and then go back
to the initial state.
So that makes tree search in
real-world environments hard.
And then there's also the
safety and cost issues.
So ideally, we want to
do model-based planning.
Imagine, you have a world
model that at each stage,
you can trigger the world
model to simulate the outcome
of each candidate action.
Then that gives you a chance
to evaluate the long-term value
and the safety of
each candidate action
before you have to commit to it.
Then you find the most
promising candidate actions
through simulation.
Then you commit to it, take
it, assuming it's safe.
And then you get
to another stage,
then you can do
this all over again.
So it's faster and safer
compared with tree search.
And you can also still do
systematic exploration,
but the downside is really how
to get this magical world model.
Let's start with,
what is a world model?
Because this is another
overloaded term.
For our purpose here, we'll
take this definition--
it's a computational model
of the environment transition
dynamics.
So basically, if I do this right
now, what would happen next?
Very simple.
Then if it's that
simple and it's
so good, why hasn't it been
done for language agents yet?
Well, the issue here
is, if you think
about word models in the classic
deep learning literature, that's
usually studied in
reinforcement learning, deep RL,
where you have these simple
simulated environments that you
can do millions of
times of trials,
and then you can use that
to learn a world model
for that simple environment.
What we're dealing with here is
much more complicated, even just
for a single website,
there could be hundreds
of different web pages.
On a single web
page, there could
be hundreds of
different actions,
and they can be constantly
changing, because the back end
database is changing.
And then this complexity
quickly compounds
if we consider that there are
billions of other websites
out there.
In that sense, we need
a generalist world model
for the internet.
That seems very hard.
Fortunately, we find that LLMs
can actually reasonably predict
these state transitions.
So in this example, if you ask
an LLM, if I click this icon,
what will happen?
Then it can recognize
that, hey, this is a shirt.
And this is probably a product.
So the next state will probably
be about some product details.
And because it's
a shirt, so there
will be sizing options
and other things.
Because LLMs have this
common sense knowledge
is trained on the internet so
it can do a reasonable job.
Far from perfect,
but reasonable.
So WebDreamer
leverages exactly that.
We simulate a world model
for the internet using
LLM, in this case, GPT-4o.
Then when you're at a state, you
have a few candidate actions.
You can use the world model
to simulate the outcome
of each candidate action.
You can even do
multistep simulation.
You have another value function,
which is also simulated by LLM
to tell you how much
progress you would
have made going down that path.
And then you can choose
the highest valued action.
You take that action,
get to the next state,
and then do this all over again.
So that's model-based
planning for web agents.
It's far from perfect, but it's
a reasonable starting point.
In terms of results, we
evaluated on VisualWebArena use.
So that model-based
planning is more accurate
than reactive planning and
slightly trails tree search.
But remember, tree
search is only possible
because we are working in a
sandbox environment, which
is VisualWebArena.
If it's on the real websites,
then backtracking in tree search
will become hard.
And also, the
model-based planning
is much cheaper and much faster.
OK?
So the takeaways for planning.
I think, language agents are
expanding into this new planning
scenarios, categorized by
the expressive but fuzzy goal
specifications, the open-ended
action spaces, and the more
difficult goal tests.
But the language for reasoning
enables new planning abilities,
like the word models,
model-based planning.
And we didn't talk about today,
but the hierarchical planning
and dynamic replanning
is also very important.
And the best planning strategy
is dependent on the LLM.
If you have a stronger base LLM,
it may require less scaffolding,
so a planning strategy
could be more reactive.
But generally, how to
improve planning in LLMs
is still largely
an open question.
I think, many people are
trying the recipe for o1 style
reasoning, try to see whether
that works for planning,
but that's still a
big open question.
OK.
So I think, we're
really just standing
at the dawn of a long journey.
We talked about planning,
reasoning, world models,
and memory.
But there are a lot of other
things we didn't talk about.
And there's a lot to be done.
Just a few immediate
future directions
I find it interesting.
I think, memory,
personalization,
and continued
learning, we are really
just scratching the surface.
There is a whole lot to be done.
How to enable agents
to continually learn
from use and exploration?
The reasoning, how to make
o1 or R1-style reasoning work
for language agents,
where you need
to deal with these fuzzy worlds
without reliable rewards?
And how to integrate
these external actions
and environmental states?
And that's a big, open question.
And I expect, there will be a
lot of study on this in 2025.
Then planning, how to build
better world models instead
of just simulator one?
And how to balance the reactive
and model-based planning?
Because you don't really
want to do simulation
at every single step,
that's very costly.
Even though humans
can do simulation,
we don't do that for
every single decision,
only for those difficult ones.
But how to balance this reactive
and model-based planning
is still an open question.
How to sustain a long horizon?
Then for safety, I think that's
a very pressing issue that
really keeps me up at night.
I think, the attack
surface of language agents
is scarily broad.
For web agents,
the attack surface
is essentially the
entire internet.
Someone can embed something
on a seemingly benign website.
And for example, OpenAI
deep research agent
can go there, visit there,
and get tricked by it,
and then maybe reveal your
private information and things
like that.
So there are two general
types of safety issues.
There's the endogenous risks.
So these are the safety
risks originate from within,
from the agent itself,
usually, because
of the incompetency
of the agent.
So it can mistakenly take
some irreversible actions
that do harm.
And then there are
exogenous risks.
So these are the risks from
the external environment.
OK?
But there are also a lot
of exciting applications.
Probably, the one with the
most clear business case
is a genetic search
or deep research.
If you have not used
[INAUDIBLE] Pro,
or Google OpenAI deep
research, I highly
encourage you to try that.
And I think, something
big is being baked here.
I think this will become
a huge thing in 2025.
Then the, also,
workflow automation.
And personally, I'm very
excited about developing agents
for sciences.
These are all very exciting.
So for a more comprehensive
coverage on language agents,
I encourage you to
check out our tutorial
with Diyi, Shunyu, and Tao.
We just did at EMNLP
two months ago.
And all the materials,
like slides and videos,
are available on our website.
I thank all of my sponsors, and
be happy to take any questions.